Guide to the William Reginald Wheeler papers, 1927-1957
Wheeler, William Reginald papers, 1927-1957
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
William Reginald Wheeler papers, 1927-1957.
4284
William Reginald Wheeler, 1889-1963.
.5 cubic ft.
Personal correspondence.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Personal correspondence, 1927-1957; documentation on agricultural work in China, 1927; athletics, 1933; Chinese women, 1935; foreign missionaries in China, 1934-1935; observations and eyewitness accounts by missionaries and teachers at Nanking ("The Nanking Incident of March 24-25, 1927").
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
American missionary and army officer.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Personal correspondence, 1927-1957; documentation on agricultural work in China, 1927; athletics, 1933; Chinese women, 1935; foreign missionaries in China, 1934-1935; observations and eyewitness accounts by missionaries and teachers at Nanking ("The Nanking Incident of March 24-25, 1927"), including the murder of John E. Williams, a missionary serving in Nanking who was also vice president of the University of Nanking; China Information Service, 1932, 1937-1938; Yale in China reports, 1947-1949; Ginling College and the University of Nanking; North China and Peking, 1934-1936; suffering of the Chinese people during the civil war in China, 1927-1936; the Japanese invasion of Manchuria in 1931; Chiang Kai-shek and the Kuo-mintang government; extracts from the diary of an American surgeon, Dr. Robert Wilson in Nanking, 1937-1938, and the atrocities he saw perpetrated by Japanese soldiers on the Chinese civilian population; the murders of the missionaries John and Elisabeth Stam.
Prominent people named in the collection include H.H. Kung, Sun Yat-sen, Chiang Kai-shek, Mayling Soong (Madame Chiang Kai-shek), C.T. (Cheng-ting) Wang, John Foster Dulles, Winston S. Churchill, Mao Tse-tung, John Leighton Stuart, Douglas MacArthur, Harry S. Truman, Albert Coady Wedemeyer, Joseph W. Stillwell, and Jonathan Mayhew Wainwright.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Wheeler, W. Reginald (William Reginald), 1889-1963.; Chiang, Kai-shek, 1887-1975.; Chiang, May-ling Soong, 1897-; Churchill, Winston, 1874-1965.; Dulles, John Foster, 1888-1959.; MacArthur, Douglas, 1880-1964.; Mao Zedong, 1893-1976.; Stilwell, Joseph Warren, 1883-1946.; Stuart, John Leighton, 1876-1962.; Truman, Harry S., 1884-1972.; Wainwright, Jonathan Mayhew, 1883-1953.; Wang, Cheng-t'ing, 1882-1961.; Wedemeyer, Albert C. (Albert Coady), 1896-; Williams, John E.; Wilson, Robert.; China Information Service.; Jinling da xue.; Yale-in-China.; Zhongguo guo min dang.
Subjects:
Missionaries--China.; Missions--China--Agricultural work.; Missions--China--Educational work.; Chinese--Missions.; Atrocities--China.; Communism--China.; Education--China.; Sino-Japanese Conflict, 1937-1945.
Places:
China--History--20th century.; China--History--Civil War, 1945-1949.; China--Politics and government.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
CONTAINER LIST
- Agricultural Work in China, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- A trip to Japan, taken by professor Searle Bates in 1936,1938. (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Rev. Arthur J. Brown, 1946. (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Letters to and from Chiang Kai-Shek and Madam Chiang, 1935-1949. (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Reports on Chiang Kai-Shek, 1938. (Box 1, Folder 5)
- An Interview with Ching-wei Wang, July, 1937. (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Athletics in China, 1933. (Box 1, Folder 7)
- China Information Service; Articles, reprints 1932, 1937-1938. (Box 1, Folder 8)
- China institute in America, Inc. (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Chinese Delegation to the United Nations, 1945, 1951-1952. (Box 1, Folder 10)
- A handwriteen Chinese letter to W.R. Wheeler re the political situation in China, Sept. 11, 1950. (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Chinese women, 1935. (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Chinese Refugees from Communism by R.W. Wheeler, Feb. 1955. (Box 1, Folder 13)
- "Christian Strategy in an Era of Revolution," by Dr. David H.C. Read, June 2, 1957. (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Letters to Winston S. Churchill, 1951. (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Letters and Articles for the Crisis Decade, Edited by W.R. Wheeler. (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Committee to Defend America by Aiding Anti-Communist China, 1949-1952. (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Letters to and from John Foster Dulles, 1949-1952. (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Foreign missionaries in China, 1934-1935. (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Ginling College (University of Nanking), 1927-1928. (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Ginling College (University of Nanking), 1933-1938. (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Hampton Roads Port of Embarkation History, 1946, 1954-1955. (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Hangchow, "The City of Heaven," 1935. (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Articles by Hu Shih, 1951. (Box 1, Folder 24)
- "Our trip to Kuling," written by one of W.R. Wheeler's children, June, 1933. (Box 1, Folder 25)
- "40th Anniversary of the Founding of the Republic of China," Oct. 10, 1911-1951. (Box 1, Folder 26)
- "An Oriental Arlington" (article re Nanking burial grounds), by W.R. Wheeler (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Eyewitness accounts by missionaries and teachers at Nanking, March 23-24, 1927. (Box 1, Folder 28)
- "Impressions of China after Thirteen Years," by W. R. Wheeler (printed from "The Chinese Recorder"), Oct. 1933. (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Incidents and observations from Nanking, 1934-1949. (Box 1, Folder 30)
- University of Nanking Hospital (extracts from a diary kept by Dr. Robert Wilson, an American doctor on the staff of the Universtity of Nanking Hospital), 1937-1938. (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Nanking Incident of March 24-25, 1927. (Box 1, Folder 32)
- North China and Peiping, 1934-1936. (Box 1, Folder 33)
- Miscellaneous Items and Clippings (Box 1, Folder 34)
- "Peace and Security." Address delivered before Chaplains Association of the Army, May 17, 1938. (Box 1, Folder 35)
- Photographs. (Box 1, Folder 36)
- Letters to Rev. P.F. Price, D.D., 1926-1928. (Box 1, Folder 37)
- Correspondence and reports re Ambassador John Leighton Stuart. (Box 1, Folder 38)
- Address by T.F. Tsiang, May 24, 1948. (Box 1, Folder 39)
- "Two Temples in Nanking." (Box 1, Folder 40)
- United States Policy toward China, 1948-1955. (Box 1, Folder 41)
- An account of Cheting Thomas Wang (Chinese ambassador to America), by W.R. Wheeler. (Box 1, Folder 42)
- Letters to W.R. Wheeler, 1927, 1938, 1947-1950. (Box 1, Folder 43)
- Letters from W.R. Wheeler, 1929-1957. (Box 1, Folder 44)
- Book reviews of John E. Willaims of Nanking, by W.R. Wheeler. (Box 1, Folder 45)
- Account of Dr. Williams murder at Nanking, by W.R. Wheeler. Mar. 24, 1927. (Box 1, Folder 46)
- Tributes to John and Elisabeth Stam, Missionary martyrs, 1934-1935. (Box 1, Folder 47)
- Eulogy for Frederick J. Tooker, M.D. by W.R. Wheeler. (Box 1, Folder 48)
- Yale in China Reports, 1947-1950. (Box 1, Folder 49)
- Yenching University News, 1950. (Box 1, Folder 50)